Robert A. Taft Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Robert A. Taft Papers 1885-1980 (bulk 1938-1953)
MSS42226
Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953
522,000 items
1,451 containers plus 1 classified and 3 oversize
581 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States senator from Ohio, Republican Party leader, and lawyer. Correspondence, family and personal papers, political and legislative files, subject files, business and financial papers, speeches and writings, and other papers relating primarily to Taft's career in the Senate and to his role as a national leader in the Republican Party.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bricker, John W. (John William), 1893-1986.; Davis, Forrest, 1893-1962.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Dirksen, Everett McKinley.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Hollister, John B. (John Baker), 1890-1978.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Ingalls, David S. (David Sinton), 1899-; Klein, Julius, 1901-1984.; Lilienthal, David Eli, 1899-1981.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Manning, Helen Taft, 1891-1987.; Pringle, Henry F. (Henry Fowles), 1897-1958.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Stassen, Harold E. (Harold Edward), 1907-2001.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Taft family.; Taft, Helen Herron, 1861-1943.; Taft, Martha Wheaton Bowers, -1958.; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Taft, Robert, Jr., 1917-1993.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944.
Organizations
Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States. Congress. Senate.; Yale University.
Subjects
Education--United States.; Elections--United States.; Labor--United States.; Practice of law--Ohio--Cincinnati.; Public housing--United States.; Taxation--United States.; Veterans--United States.; World War, 1914-1918.
Places
Ohio--Politics and government.; United States--Defenses.; United States--Economic policy--20th century.; United States--Foreign relations--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--1901-1953.
Occupations
Lawyers.; Politicians.; Senators, U.S. Congress--Ohio.
Provenance
The papers of Robert A. Taft, United States senator from Ohio, Republican Party leader, and lawyer, were given to the Library of Congress from 1953 to 1983 by the Taft family. Additional material was received by gift and transfer, 1954-1987.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Sound recordings and newsreel film have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. Photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Robert A. Taft Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Robert A. Taft are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified material.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1889, Sept. 8 Born, Cincinnati, Ohio
1910 B.A. summa cum laude, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1913 LL.B. summa cum laude, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. Admitted to Ohio bar
1913 1917 Practiced law, Cincinnati, Ohio
1914 Married Martha Wheaton Bowers
1917 1919 Assistant counsel, United States Food Administration, Washington, D.C.
1919 Counsel, American Relief Administration, Paris, France
1920 Return to law practice
1921 1926 Republican member of Ohio House of Representatives; elected speaker in 1926
1931 1932 Republican member, Ohio Senate
1936 Ohio's "favorite son" for Republican presidential nomination
1939 1953 Republican member, United States Senate
1940 1952 Candidate for Republican presidential nomination (1940, 1944, 1948, and 1952)
1944 1953 Chairman, Republican Senate Policy Committee
1947 Chairman, Senate Labor and Public Welfare Committee, Eightieth Congress
1951 Published A Foreign Policy for Americans. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday
1953 Senate Majority Leader, Eighty-third Congress
1953, July 31 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Robert Alphonso Taft (1889-1953) span the years 1885-1980, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1938-1953. The papers have been organized in the following series: Family Papers, Personal File, General Correspondence, Letters Sent, Political File, Legislative Papers, Subject File, Special Files, Speeches and Writings File, Business Papers, Miscellany, Addition, Oversize, and Top Secret.
Family Papers consist of correspondence and other material documenting the lives of four generations of Tafts. Major correspondents include Robert A. Taft's parents, Helen Herron Taft and William Howard Taft, his sister, Helen Taft Manning, his wife, Martha Wheaton Bowers Taft, and his son, Robert Taft (1917-1993). There is a sizable amount of biographical material on William H. Taft, twenty-seventh president of the United States, including printed matter and correspondence with numerous individuals, among them Henry Pringle, author of The Life and Work of William Howard Taft. The series also contains letters of condolence on the death of both parents.
The Personal File reflects Taft's early law career and civic engagements in Cincinnati, Ohio; his service during World War I, which included a close association with Herbert Hoover in Washington, D.C., and Paris; and his postwar occupational and political activities in Ohio until 1927.
The General Correspondence series contains letters and other material related to Taft's numerous business enterprises and associates, his colleagues in the United States Senate, and other friends and acquaintances. This series, as a separate filing unit, was terminated in 1945; thereafter correspondence was filed as political, legislative, or general, with political and legislative correspondence filed chronologically and general correspondence filed alphabetically by subject.
The Letters Sent series consists of Taft's replies to professional correspondence received. The series serves as a locator for incoming correspondence filed under Political File, Legislative Papers, or Subject File. Typed in the top margin of each page are cross references to the original item, subject matter, and often Taft's reason for responding.
The most significant series within the collection are Political File, Legislative Papers, and Subject File. They reflect the development of Taft's political career at both the state and national levels as well as his rise to leadership within the Republican party. The bulk of the Political File concerns Taft's campaigns for the United States Senate (1938-1950) and for the Republican presidential nomination (1940-1952), with over one-third of the series relating to his bid in 1952. Also notable are files concerning his years in the Ohio state legislature, organized labor's opposition to his Senate campaign of 1950, and its consequent investigation by Congress.
The Legislative Papers relate to matters of policy and legislation either proposed or enacted into law. They include correspondence, petitions, suggestions, and inquiries concerning programs and positions taken by Taft and the Republican party on local, state, and national issues not found in the more general Subject File. There are also published committee hearings and reports, files relating to individuals, and letters containing praise, criticism, or suggestions from political leaders and the public. Subjects of note include economics, labor, defense, foreign policy, finance and taxation, and veterans.
The Subject File represents a broad spectrum of topics concerning public affairs. The series was organized in Taft's senatorial office in 1946 and was used until his death in 1953. The papers, filed chronologically and thereunder alphabetically by subject, illustrate Taft's belief that a politician should not only work for the good of his constituents and the nation as a whole, but also provide moral leadership. On the whole, Taft was a staunch believer in party unity, but at times he was also capable of taking very independent positions on political issues. This paradoxical nature is reflected on the one hand by his intense opposition to certain policies of presidents Roosevelt, Truman, and Eisenhower and on the other hand by his wholehearted support for different policies by the same presidents.
The Special File consists of material on political figures. These include Thomas E. Dewey, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Herbert Hoover, Harold E. Stassen, Adlai E. Stevenson (1900-1965), and Harry S. Truman.
The Speeches and Writings File represents a comprehensive collection of Taft's addresses, public statements, radio broadcasts, news releases, and published articles. They are arranged chronologically and thereunder alphabetically by type of material.
The Business Papers document Taft's financial investments, properties in Ohio and in Washington, D.C., philanthropic support for artistic and cultural institutions, personal finances, as well as estate papers of several Taft family members.
The Miscellany series contains appointment books, clippings, galley proofs and correspondence relating to Taft's 1951 publication A Foreign Policy for Americans, honorary degrees and citations for service, letters of condolence, material concerning both the Taft family summer home and a fish and game club in Canada, and also material documenting Taft's long relationship with his alma mater Yale University.
The Addition consists of family papers, general correspondence, political material, speeches and writings, business papers, and miscellaneous material. Of note are Martha Bowers Taft's political correspondence and speeches, illustrating her skill as campaigner and speaker in her own right as well as her more traditional role as politician's wife. There are letters from William H. Taft while chief justice of the Supreme Court to his son Robert Alphonso in which he discusses contemporary judicial topics. Also of interest is the file detailing the establishment of a memorial to the twenty-seventh president in Arlington National Cemetery. Robert A. Taft's life is chronicled by the files containing his speeches, records concerning the settling of his personal estate, clippings and other biographical material, as well as numerous letter of condolence written to both his wife and son Robert, Jr. The public's appreciation of Taft's life and achievements are evident in files documenting memorials to Taft in Cincinnati and Washington, D.C.
Oversize material consists of an architectural sketch, memorial resolutions in honor of Robert A. Taft, photostatic copies, and scrapbooks.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in fourteen series:
Family Papers, 1885-1959
Personal File, 1917-1927
General Correspondence, 1903-1945
Letters Sent, 1937-1953
Political File, 1924-1953
Legislative Papers, 1920-1953
Subject File, 1946-1953
Special Files, 1920-1953
Speeches and Writings File, 1933-1953
Business Papers, 1914-1953
Miscellany, 1907-1953
Addition, 1910-1980
Oversize, 1919-1953
Top Secret, 1948-1949
Container List
- Family Papers, 1885-1959 (Box 1-17)
  Letters sent and received by family members. Includes posthumous correspondence and biographical and photographic material relating to William H. Taft.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of individual and chronologically thereunder.
  - Taft family (Box 1)
    - Taft, Alphonso (grandfather), 1930, undated
    - Taft, Charles Phelps (brother), 1903-1953, (3 folders)
    - Taft, Charles Phelps (uncle), 1918
    - Taft, Harriet (sister), 1906, undated
    - Taft, Helen (sister) See also Container 17, Manning, Frederick J. and Helen Taft
      - 1903-1916, (2 folders)
      - Undated (Box 2)
    - Taft, Helen Herron (mother)
      - Correspondence with Robert A. Taft, 1905-1943, undated, (6 folders)
      - Death (Box 3)
        - Letters of condolence, 1943, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 4)
        - Memorial book, 1943
        - Sympathy cards, 1943
    - Taft, Henry (uncle), 1925-1945
    - Taft, Horace Dwight (uncle)
      - 1906-1936, (3 folders)
      - 1937-1942, (1 folder)
      - Estate papers, 1939-1945
      - Memories and Opinions, correspondence, 1939-1947, undated
    - Taft, Horace Dwight (son), 1940-1945
    - Taft, Hulbert (uncle), 1909-1951, (2 folders)
    - Taft, Lloyd Bowers (son), 1937-1943
    - Taft, Martha Bowers (wife) See also Containers 16-17, Bowers Family, general (Box 6)
      - Correspondence
        - With Robert A. Taft
          - 1912-1945, undated, (7 folders)
          - Undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
      - With others
        - 1908-1940, (6 folders)
        - 1941-1953, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - Taft, miscellaneous family members
      - Correspondence, 1913-1953, (2 folders)
      - General, 1895-1941, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Taft School, Watertown, Conn., 1934-1940, (3 folders)
    - Taft, Robert (1917-1993) (son)
      - 1933-1944, (4 folders)
      - 1945-1953, undated, (4 folders) (Box 10)
    - Taft, William H. (father)
      - Biographical material
        - Correspondence about William H. Taft
          - General
            - 1905-1931, (7 folders)
            - 1932-1950, (8 folders) (Box 11)
            - 1950
              - Jan.-May
              - June-Dec., (2 folders) (Box 12)
            - 1952-1953, undated, (4 folders)
        - Pringle, Henry, re Life and Work of William Howard Taft, 1930-1951, (6 folders) (Box 13)
      - Printed matter, (5 folders); (1 folder) (Box 14, Box 15)
      - Correspondence
        - With Robert A. Taft
          - 1903-1925, (6 folders)
          - 1926-1928, (3 folders) (Box 16)
        - With others, 1885, 1924-1927
      - Death, letters of condolence, 1930
    - Taft, William Howard (1915 Aug. 7- ) (son), 1944-1953
    - Bowers family
      - General
        - 1901-1914, (3 folders)
  - Other family members (Box 17)
    - Bowers family
      - General
        - 1942-1943, undated, (2 folders)
      - Bowers, Thomas Wilson (brother-in-law), 1901-1959, (4 folders)
    - Ingalls, David S. (cousin), 1926-1943
    - Manning, Frederick J. and Helen Taft (brother-in-law and sister), 1933-1953, undated, (3 folders)
- Personal File, 1917-1927 (Box 18-20)
  Correspondence and records concerning Taft's law practice and civic activities in Cincinnati, Ohio, the selective service, United States Food Administration in Washington, D.C., and American Relief Administration in Paris, France.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically thereunder.
  - American Field Service Fellowship, 1923 (Box 18)
  - American Legion controversy, 1925
  - American Relief Administration
    - 1918-1922, (2 folders)
    - Children's Fund, 1919-1924
  - Cincinnati, Ohio
    - Bar association, 1926
    - Bonds and city plan, 1921
    - Charter commission, 1917, 1926, (2 folders)
    - City budget, 1922
    - City Council streetcar ordinance, 1925
    - Mayor's Taxation Committee, 1920 (Box 19)
  - Cincinnatus Association, 1920-1921
  - Civic League, 1921
  - Documents from Europe, 1917-1919
  - Law practice papers
    - 1920-1927
    - Statements for service, 1919-1924, (2 folders)
    - Stewart v. Brown
      - 1923-1924
      - Ohio taxation
    - Telephone rate case, 1920-1923
    - Mayor's budget, tax rates and statistics, 1921
  - Military selective service, 1917 (Box 20)
  - Mischler, Wendell, 1918-1927
  - Ohio ex rel. Keller v. Tax Commission, 1923
  - Ohio
    - State bar association, 1926
    - Tax Association Committee, 1924
  - Ohio taxation, McCrehen v. Brown, O.S.C. No. 18199, 1923
  - The Pillars, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1922-1926
  - Social unit experiment, 1919-1920
  - Sulgrave Institution, New York, N.Y., 1922
  - Taft, William H., and Woodrow Wilson, interview, 1917
  - University Club of Cincinnati, Ohio, 1921
  - Wilberforce University, Wilberforce, Ohio, appointments, 1926
- General Correspondence, 1903-1945 (Box 20-34)
  Letters sent and received and miscellaneous material related to Taft's business enterprises, Senate colleagues, and other friends. Also included is a container of general correspondence related to Martha Bowers Taft.
  Arranged chronologically and alphabetically thereunder according to name of person, organization, geographic address, or subject.
  - Chronological file (Box 20)
    - 1898, 1903-1914, (6 folders)
    - 1915-1926, (10 folders) (Box 21)
    - 1927-1929, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    - 1929-1930, (6 folders) (Box 23)
    - 1931-1932, miscellaneous and unidentified, (7 folders) (Box 24)
    - 1933-1935, (7 folders) (Box 25)
    - 1935-1936, miscellaneous and unidentified, (9 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1937-1938, miscellaneous and unidentified, (8 folders) (Box 27)
    - 1939-1940, miscellaneous, (7 folders) (Box 28)
    - 1940-1941, miscellaneous, (6 folders) (Box 29)
    - 1941-1942, miscellaneous and unidentified, (9 folders) (Box 30)
    - 1943-1944, miscellaneous, (9 folders) (Box 31)
    - 1945-1948, (6 folders) (Box 32)
    - 1949-1953, undated, (7 folders) (Box 33)
  - Alphabetical file (Box 34)
    - Clippinger, John H., 1939-1945
    - Dewey, Thomas E., 1944-1945
    - Dykstra, Mr. & Mrs. C. A., 1934-1935, 1951
    - Finch, Roy, 1939-1943
    - French, Robert D., 1929-1945
    - Harrison, George L., 1913-1936, 1925-1940
    - Herron, Jon W., 1926, 1934-1943
    - Hewes, Thomas, 1936, 1945-1952
    - Hollister, John B., 1927-1952, undated
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1922-1953
    - Klein, Julius, 1941-1945
    - Marshall, John, 1944-1952
    - More, John H., 1927-1945
    - Noojin, Mrs. B. L. (Billie), 1945-1951
    - Taft, Siegfried, 1947-1948
    - Zuzer, Worth, 1944-1948
    - Miscellaneous, 1939-1953
- Letters Sent, 1937-1953 (Box 35-98)
  Copies of replies to professional correspondence.
  Arranged chronologically and alphabetically thereunder by name of person or organization.
  - 1937-1946, (7 folders) (Box 35)
  - 1947-1949, (7 folders) (Box 36)
  - 1949-1951, (9 folders) (Box 37)
  - 1951 (Box 38)
    - Ai-Az, (7 folders)
    - Ba-Ca, (8 folders) (Box 39)
    - Ce-Dy, (10 folders) (Box 40)
    - Ea-Go, (11 folders) (Box 41)
    - Gr-Ha, (9 folders) (Box 42)
    - He-Hr, (9 folders) (Box 43)
    - Hu-Jo, (12 folders) (Box 44)
    - Jo-Ky, (12 folders) (Box 45)
    - La-Ly, (11 folders) (Box 46)
    - McA-Ma, (11 folders) (Box 47)
    - Ma-My, (8 folders) (Box 48)
    - Na-Ne, (7 folders) (Box 49)
    - Ni-Pa, (11 folders) (Box 50)
    - Pa-Q, (9 folders) (Box 51)
    - Ra-Ry, (8 folders) (Box 52)
    - Sa-Sh, (7 folders) (Box 53)
    - Si-St, (12 folders) (Box 54)
    - St-Tk, (9 folders) (Box 55)
    - To-Vz, (12 folders) (Box 56)
    - W-Wh, (6 folders) (Box 57)
    - Wi-Zu, (8 folders) (Box 58)
  - 1952 (Box 59)
    - Aa-Ap, (11 folders)
    - Ar-Az, (8 folders) (Box 60)
    - Ba-Bl, (7 folders) (Box 61)
    - Bo-By, (8 folders) (Box 62)
    - C-Cl, (9 folders) (Box 63)
    - Co-Da, (9 folders) (Box 64)
    - De-Ek, (11 folders) (Box 65)
    - Em-Fo, (10 folders) (Box 66)
    - Fr-Gy, (11 folders) (Box 67)
    - Ha-He, (7 folders) (Box 68)
    - Hi-Iz, (11 folders) (Box 69)
    - Ja-Ki, (9 folders) (Box 70)
    - Kl-Li, (15 folders) (Box 71)
    - Ll-McW, (13 folders) (Box 72)
    - Ma-Mi, (8 folders) (Box 73)
    - Ml-Ne, (10 folders) (Box 74)
    - Ni-Pa, (14 folders) (Box 75)
    - Pe-Ra, (10 folders) (Box 76)
    - Ra-Ry, (8 folders) (Box 77)
    - Sa-Sl, (11 folders) (Box 78)
    - Sm-Sz, (13 folders) (Box 79)
    - Ta-V, (11 folders) (Box 80)
    - Ve-We, (8 folders) (Box 81)
    - Wl-Z, (8 folders) (Box 82)
  - 1953 (Box 83)
    - A-Ar, (9 folders)
    - As-Bo, (7 folders) (Box 84)
    - Br-Cl, (8 folders) (Box 85)
    - Co-Dr, (11 folders) (Box 86)
    - Du-Fo, (8 folders) (Box 87)
    - Fo-Gy, (6 folders) (Box 88)
    - Ha-Ho, (9 folders) (Box 89)
    - Hr-Kn, (13 folders) (Box 90)
    - Ko-McK, (9 folders) (Box 91)
    - McN-Na, (13 folders) (Box 92)
    - Ne-Pl, (13 folders) (Box 93)
    - Po-Ro, (10 folders) (Box 94)
    - Ru-Sm, (11 folders) (Box 95)
    - Sm-Ta, (9 folders) (Box 96)
    - Te-Wa, (15 folders) (Box 97)
  - 1953 (Box 98)
    - We-Zu, (14 folders)
- Political File, 1924-1953 (Box 99-471)
  Letters received and sent, Republican party activities, statements, news releases, clippings, and texts of radio broadcasts, campaign literature, petitions, primary and general election materials, states subject files, minorities activities, patronage matters, and voter lists.
  Filed chronologically by campaign and alphabetically thereunder by type of material or name of person, organization, or subject.
  - 1924-1938, Election statistics, (3 folders) (Box 99)
  - 1927-1934, Hamilton County, Ohio, Republican Club, (2 folders)
  - 1927, Republican Executive Committee
  - 1928, Cincinnati Hoover-for President Campaign, Cincinnati, Ohio, check book and receipts
  - 1928-1929, Republican Executive Committee, (2 folders)
  - 1929, Statistics
  - 1930
    - General correspondence, (3 folders)
    - Republican
      - Executive Committee
      - Nominating Committee
    - Stable Money Association (Box 100)
  - 1931
    - General correspondence, (2 folders)
    - Reapportionment of congressional districts
    - Republican Executive Committee, Hamilton County, Ohio
  - 1932
    - Clippings
    - General correspondence, (3 folders)
    - Republican Executive Committee, Hamilton County, Ohio
  - 1933
    - General correspondence
    - Hamilton County, Ohio, Relief Committee
    - Republican Executive Committee Hamilton County, Ohio, (3 folders)
  - 1934 (Box 101)
    - Durr-Tudor Contest
    - Ohio State Campaign Committee
    - Republican Executive Committee, Hamilton County, Ohio, (4 folders)
  - 1934-1935
    - City politics and finances, (2 folders) (Box 102)
    - County campaign material, (4 folders)
  - 1934-1936, Ohio Executive Committee on Infantile Paralysis
  - 1935-1937, Cincinnati, Ohio, taxes
  - 1935
    - General correspondence
    - New Charter, Hamilton County, Ohio, (2 folders); (1 folder) (Box 103)
    - Local Politics
    - New Charter, Hamilton County, Ohio
    - Republican Executive Committee, Hamilton County, Ohio, (2 folders)
  - 1936
    - Cincinnati Chamber of Commerce, Cincinnati, Ohio
    - Local politics, (4 folders)
    - Ohio Chamber of Commerce
    - National politics, (1 folder); (6 folders) (Box 104)
    - Proportional representation, (2 folders)
    - Republican Executive Committee, Hamilton County, Ohio, (1 folder) (Box 105)
    - Republican National Committee, (4 folders)
  - 1937
    - Columbia Township, Ohio, (3 folders)
    - Republican Executive Committee, Hamilton County, Ohio, (2 folders)
  - 1938 (Box 106)
    - National pPolitics, (3 folders)
    - Absent voters
    - Advertising
    - Applications
    - Bada, William K.
    - Bali-Curry correspondence
    - Businessmen
    - Clippinger, John
    - List of Taft representatives
    - Newspaper clippings, (3 folders)
    - Newspaper weeklies (Box 107)
    - Campaign, press clippings
      - State
        - Alabama
        - Arizona
        - Arkansas
        - California
        - Colorado
        - Connecticut
        - Florida
        - Georgia
        - Idaho
        - Illinois
        - Indiana
        - Iowa
        - Kansas
        - Kentucky
        - Louisiana
        - Maine
        - Massachusetts
        - Michigan
        - Minnesota
        - Mississippi
        - Missouri